Husband Left 8 Years Ago.
How to Raise Children Well
My husband was a habitual liar who
lied to me about his and his family's
educational levels, his job,
even his birthday before we were married.
I found out later, but I thought
he must have had his reasons.
I decided to overlook it and
got married believing
that he would be different after marriage.
Now, I am reaping what I sowed.
When my children were 5 and 3,
he left without a word,
taking all our savings of
$20,000 and his clothes.
8 years have passed, now my
children are in 6th and 4th grades.
They are growing up well,
doing well in school.
Though I am raising them alone,
I am really enjoying them.
I've heard virtuous deeds can be
reaped by your children if not by you.
I've not sown good karma,
only bad karma
and I ended up scarring my children
of growing up without a father.
I have a wish.
How can I reap all the bad karma sown
myself and not pass it down to my children?
You had a rough time living alone?
(Questioner) At first,
I felt wronged and angry.
As much as wronged and angry you felt,
you will receive due consequences.
If you lived without those harsh feelings,
you would receive blessings.
(Sunim) In any case,
I know you have suffered.
Has your husband contacted
you since then?
(Questioner) No, I have not
heard from him.
That's a relief. (Audience Laughter)
It would be terrible
if he showed up asking for money.
(Questioner) Yes, I am grateful for that.
(Questioner Laughter)
Are you divorced legally or not?
(Questioner) I am.
Legally done?
(Questioner) Yes.
What a relief. Now.
it's in the past.
It's not happening now.
It's in the past.
You may say your husband was a bad guy
lying to you about his education and such.
But, he probably lied to you because
he wanted to marry you, right?
(Questioner) Yes.
If he had told you the truth, you
would not have chosen him, right?
If he had been honest about himself
and his family while dating,
you would not have married him, right?
(Sunim) Would you still
have married him?
Yes.
But, he thought if he revealed the truth,
you wouldn't marry him.
Is there a possibility that he thought so?
(Questioner) Yes.
That's why he lied.
Because he wanted to marry you.
How desperate he must have been to
marry you that he would even lie?
So you could feel pity for him.
You should consider,
"How desperate he must
have felt to marry me
that he lied like that."
And so you got married and
had two children, right?
(Questioner) Yes.
These days, in places like France,
there are women who want to
have a child, without getting married.
Are they able to do that or not?
Can they have babies without
getting married, or not?
(Questioner) They can.
Yes, they can.
They go to sperm banks,
pay for the sperm and
get artificially inseminated
to have a baby.
Do they pay for the sperms, or not?
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner)They do.
(Questioner Laughter)
Is it free or do they have to pay?
(Questioner) (Sunim) They have to pay.
But, you got the sperms for free.
(Audience Laughter)
So that you had two children.
This man could have stayed
and continued to lie.
That would have been hard
for you and would have been
bad influence on your children.
But he donated his sperms and left.
Whose gain is it?
It is mine.
(Audience Laughter)
(Sunim) So, paying $20,000
for it was not so bad, was it?
Yes, I think it was cheap for..
(Questioner Laughter)
Yes, it was cheap.
(Audience Laughter)(Questioner Laughter)
And you had some fun, too.
So, think this way and just drop
the whole thing. Don't dwell on it.
(Questioner) Yes.
Without dwelling on it
any longer, just let it go.
You think the kids are scarred
because they don't have a father,
but that is not the case.
There may be a bit of negative effects,
but it is not because
they don't have a father.
Your feeling of loneliness and hardship
affects your children negatively.
In the end, it is said that no father
will affect the children negatively.
(Questioner) That is
what I am most afraid of.
It is not directly caused
by not having husband.
Even without a husband,
say you went to a sperm bank and
bought the sperms and got a baby.
Would you feel lonely and
inadequate without a husband?
No, not at all. Not having a father will
not have negative effect on the child.
(Sunim) Do you understand
what I am saying?
Yes.
So, the child having a problem is not
due to the fact that he has no father.
The problem arises when
the mother is having a hard time
because she has no husband.
Her difficulties will cause
the child to have problems.
Children are not troubled
if the father comes home drunk.
It's the mother struggling
with a drunken husband,
that affects the children negatively.
So, even if the husband comes
home drunk and acts up,
if the wife understands him and say
" Honey, you had a lot to drink today.
What are you going to talk
about today? Tell me." (Audience Laughter)
If she doesn't call it a drunken fit
and listen to what he has to say,
pat him on the back and put him to sleep,
it won't affect the children at all.
The impact on the children comes from
the mother's handling of the husband,
and how it is reflected
back on the children.
His behavior does not
have a direct effect.
So, if you are confident
about being a single mom,
the children will have no problem.
The problem of no father arises
when the kids ask about their father,
and you recoil with trembling heart.
(Sunim) You wonder what you should say.
You feel the inferiority complex.
Then they feel inferior
about not having a father.
When they are young,
you can just say he is living abroad.
And when they become teenagers, you can
tell them the truth that you are divorced.
You can say this without any feeling of
inferiority complex, smiling
even, they may be a bit shocked
but it will not be a big problem.
But, if you get all emotional
and upset and say
"Your father took all the money and
left us after a few years of marriage.
(Audience Laughter)
I struggled to raise you"
Then to them the father is a bad guy.
This will, in turn, wound them with scars.
They will hate the father
but miss him also.
All kinds of feelings will get entangled.
There will be many scars, not just one.
So, you must live confidently now.
If you want a man, get married again.
Don't think that you can't
marry because of the kids.
If you get married and live happily,
the kids will be happy, too.
(Sunim) Maybe you won't marry.
But, you got the sperms really
cheap and got two children.
Aren't you happy that
you have your children?
(Questioner) Yes, I am happy.
Sure.
They are presents from your husband.
He had problems as a human being,
but he left you nice presents.
(Questioner) Yes.
Keep that attitude.
So should you say nice things
about their father, or bad things?
(Questioner) Nice things.
Nice things. Then the children
won't have any problems.
(Questioner) Okay.
But, you won't be able to do it.
You say yes now, (Audience Laughter)
but your heart won't move.
You keep thinking that he lied to you
before marriage, then during marriage.
These things are still on your mind
and you still have a scar.
So do 108 bows every day.
"Thank you. Thank you.
You didn’t cause us any harm".
"Thank you for giving me
two wonderful children".
If you do these prayers of gratitude,
your children won't have any problem.
(Questioner) Do I have to do
the prayer of repentance to my husband?
Do the prayer of gratitude.
For leaving you the gifts.
(Audience Laughter)
(Questioner Laughter)
(Questioner) Yes, thank you.